Berwyn, Ill. North Berwyn Congregational Church records, 1910-1999.
Congregational Library & Archives
Berwyn, Ill. North Berwyn Congregational Church records, 1910-1999.
RG5558
Congregational Library & Archives
1.79 Cubic Feet
(3 boxes)
On February 8, 1910, the North Berwyn Congregational Church was formally established. It was initially supported, financially, by the First Church of Oak Park before being supported by the Chicago Congregational Union, later known as the Chicago City Missionary Society. After nearly closing during the Great Depression, the church building was expanded in 1938. A new church building was constructed in 1956 and this building too received an expansion almost a decade later. The church joined with the United Church of Christ. Membership declined after the North Berwyn community changed during the 1970s. The church dissolved circa 2008. This collection contains both administrative and membership related materials and includes church records, annual reports, council records, newsletters, histories, and membership records.
North Berwyn Congregational Church (Berwyn, Ill.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Illinois Conference of the United Church of Christ in December 2024; accession number 2024-46.
Custodial History
The materials in this collection were given to the Illinois Conference of the United Church of Christ, likely around the time of the church's dissolution. There is no further documentation on how the materials arrived at the Illinois Conference.
Historical Note
By 1906, the First Church of Oak Park was involved in multiple home missionary projects within the growing community of northern Berwyn, a Chicago suburb. These projects including supporting a Sunday School and a Women's Aid Society in the community. In 1909, Rev. F. V. Bastel was called to become the leader of these missionary efforts. At this time, serious thought was put into establishing a permanent church in the neighborhood. In December 1909, a petition of more than 30 persons was presented to the First Church of Oak Park requesting the formal establishment of the North Berwyn Congregational Church. On February 8, 1910, the church was formally established and the First Church of Oak Park was the primary financial source for the church until 1914. After the establishment of the church, Rev. George Milne was called to become the church's pastor.
After 1914, financial support for the church was transferred to the Chicago Congregational Union, later known as the Chicago City Missionary Society. The church nearly closed, as the suggestion of the Chicago Congregational Union, during the Great Depression, but the small numbers of members at the time managed to keep the church active. The church saw growth again after the great depression and expanded their church building in response with the dedication for the expansion held in May 1938.
The church continued to see growth throughout the 1940s and 1950s. By the mid-1950s, the church saw the need for a new church building. A new church building was constructed in 1956 with the dedication in October of that year. At the same time, the church became financially solvent and no longer needed financial assistance from the Chicago City Missionary Society. The church building saw another extension in the 1960s. The church also joined with the United Church of Christ following the denominations formation in 1957.
By 1970, the population of North Berwyn had seen significant changes, with many moving further out to the suburbs and the Catholic community growing. Between 1971 and 1974, the North Berwyn Congregational Church shared a pastor with the Plymouth Congregational Church in Maywood. In 1979, the church fully payed off the mortgage and celebrated with a mortgage burning. During the 1980s and beyond, the church worked closely with the wider North Berwyn community, participating in ecumenical events and opening up the church as a space for community and secular groups to gather. The North Berwyn Congregational Church dissolved circa 2008.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the administrative records of the North Berwyn Congregational Church as well as records documenting the activities of church's members. The collection contains church records and meeting minutes, council records and meeting minutes, annual reports, building and financial records, newsletters, church histories, a historical scrapbook, and membership records.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the two series listed below. Materials within each series have been arranged primarily by chronological order, with continuous materials grouped together.
Series 1: Administrative records, 1910-1992
Series 1: Membership and church activities, 1921-1999
Baptismal records.; Church membership.; Church newsletters.; Church records and registers.; Marriage records.; Necrologies.; Women -- Societies and clubs.; Berwyn (Ill.) -- Church history.; North Berwyn Congregational Church (Berwyn, Ill.)
- Administrative records, 1910 1992; 1910-1992
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the governance and daily business of the North Berwyn Congregational Church. This series includes church records and meeting minutes, board of deacons records and meeting minutes, council records and meeting minutes, committee records, annual reports, and financial records.
  - Ecclesiastical council letter missive, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Church records, 1910 1931; 1910-1931 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    Separated Materials
    Loose materials in this volume were removed and placed in the folder labeled "Membership records, 1921-1937" for preservation purposes.
  - Church records, 1932 1942; 1932-1942 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Loose materials were removed from this volume and placed into the folders labeled "Miscellaneous records, 1938-1957" and "Church cabinet meeting minutes, 1935-1936" for preservation purposes.
  - Church records, 1942 1947; 1942-1947 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Church records, 1946 1952; 1946-1952 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Church records, 1952 1958; 1952-1958 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Church cabinet meeting minutes, 1935 1936; 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    These materials were removed from the "Church records, 1932-1942" volume for preservation purposes.
  - Building and financial records, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous records, 1938 1957; 1938-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - financial graphs, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Board of deacons and deaconesses minutes, 1941 1944; 1941-1944 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  - Board of deacons records, 1942 1949; 1942, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of deacons records, 1955 1964; 1955-1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board of deacons records, 1958 1962; 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Board of trustees records, 1941 1954; 1941-1954 (Box 1, Volume 7)
  - Board of trustees records, 1955 1958; 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual reports, 1942 1991; 1942, 1954, 1989, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Building committee records, 1950 1954; 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Year book report, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Various church and committee records, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Various church and committee records, 1968 1970; 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Constitutions, 1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Council records, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Council records, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Council records, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Council meeting minutes, 1972 1974; 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Council meeting minutes, 1990 1992; 1990, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Membership and church activities, 1921 1999; 1921-1999
  This series contains records related to the activities of members of the North Berwyn Congregational Church. The series includes newsletters, men's club records, women's society records, photographs, church histories, and a historical scrapbook.
  - History scrapbook, 1902 1999; 1902-1999 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Confirmation class lists, 1913 1955; 1913-1955 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Membership records, 1921 1937; 1921-1937 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    These materials were removed from the "Church records, 1910-1931" volume for preservation purposes.
  - Women's Society records, 1922 1952; 1922-1952 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    These materials were removed from the "Women's society minutes, 1941-1953" volume for preservation purposes.
  - The Messenger newsletter, 1925 1928; 1925-1928 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Messenger newsletter, 1929 1932; 1929-1932 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Church histories, 1936, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Men's club records, 1936 1940; 1936, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Neighborhood News newsletter, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Women's society minutes, 1941 1953; 1941-1953 (Box 1, Volume 8)
    Loose materials were removed from this volume and placed into the folder labeled "Women's Society records, 1922-1952" for preservation purposes.
  - Special events and anniversaries, 1941 1963; 1941-1963 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - N.B.C.C. Broadcaster newsletter, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Women's society history, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Pilgrim fellowship meeting minutes, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Membership list, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Congrenews newsletter, 1964 1966; 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photos of lots 30 and 31 at corner of Oak Park Avenue and 13th Street, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)